<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three letters</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62489</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1099</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1356</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11950136</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11950136</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51366</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62489)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51366)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 517:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three letters</title>
                  <author>Petre, Edward, 1631-1699. Lettre du R.P. Peters, Jesuite, premier aumonier du roi d'Angle terre, ecrite au R.P. La Chaize, confesseur du roi tres-Chrêtien. English.</author>
                  <author>La Chaise, François d'Aix de, 1624-1709. Antwoort van den eerwaerdigen vader La chaise, biechtvader van den arder-christelyckten Koninck, op den brief van den eerwaerdigen vader Peters, Jesuit en eersten aelmoessenier van den Koninck van Engelandt. English.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>I. A letter from a Jesuit at Liege, to a Jesuit at Fribourg, giving an account of the happy progress of religion in England -- II. A letter from the Reverend Father Petre, Jesuit, almoner to the King of England, written to the Reverend Father LaChese, confessour to the most Christian king, touching the present affairs of England -- III. The answer of the Reverend Father La Chese, confessour to the most Christian King, to a letter of the Reverend Father Petre, Jesuit, and great almoner to the King of England, upon the method or rule he must observe with His Maiesty, for the conversion of his Protestant subjects.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51366:1"/>
            <head>THREE LETTERS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> A Letter from a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> at <hi>Liege,</hi> to a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> at <hi>Fribourg,</hi> giving an Account of the Happy Progreſs of Religion in <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT cannot be ſaid what great affection and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the K. hath for the Society, wiſhing much health to this whole Colledge by <hi>R. P.</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial, and earneſtly recommending himſelf to our Prayers. The Provincial <hi>Alexander Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> being come back for <hi>England,</hi> the K. was graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed to ſend for him; (ſeveral Earls and Dukes waiting his coming at the hour appointed) the Q. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent, the King diſcourſing familiarly with him, asked him <hi>How many young Students he had, and how many Scholaſticks?</hi> to which (when the Provincial had anſwered, That of the latter he had Twenty, of the former more than Fifty) he added, <hi>That he had need of double or treable that number to perform what he in his mind had deſigned for the Society;</hi> and commanded that they ſhould be very well exerciſed in the gift of Preaching; <hi>for ſuch only</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>do we want in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
               <p>You have heard I make no doubt, that the K. hath ſent Letters to Father <hi>Le Cheſe,</hi> the French King's Confeſſor about <hi>Wadden</hi>-houſe, therein declaring, that he would take in good part from him, whatſoever he did or was done for the Engliſh Fathers of that Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Father <hi>Clare</hi> Rector of the ſaid Houſe going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe Affairs at <hi>London,</hi> found an eaſie acceſs to the K. and as eaſily obtained his deſires. He was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid to kneel and kiſs the Kings hand (as the manner or cuſtom is) by the K. himſelf, ſaying, <hi>Once indeed your Reverence kiſſed my hand, but had I then known you were a Prieſt, I ſhould rather have kneeled and kiſſed your Reverences hand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the buſineſs was ended, in a familiar Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, the K. declared to this Father, <hi>That he would either Convert</hi> England, <hi>or dye a Martyr; and that he had rather die tomorrow, that Converſion wrought, than Reign Fifty years without that, in happineſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity.</hi> Laſtly, he called himſelf <hi>a Son of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> the Welfare of which, he ſaid, He as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced at as his own: And it can ſcarce be ſaid how joyful he ſhewed himſelf when it was told him That he was made partaker, by the moſt Reverend Father <hi>N.</hi> of all the Merits of the Society; of which number he would declare one of his Confeſſors: Some report <hi>R. P.</hi> the Provincial will be the perſon, but whom he deſigns it not yet known. Many do think an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick will be beſtowed on Father <hi>Edmond Petre,</hi> (chiefly beloved) very many a Cardinals Cap, to whom, (within this Month or two) that whole part of the K. Palace is granted, in which the K. when he was Duke of <hi>York</hi> uſed to reſide; where you may ſee I know not how many Courtiers daily attending to ſpeak with his Eminency, (for ſo they are ſaid to call him) upon whoſe councel, and alſo that of ſeveral Catholick Peers, highly preferred in the Kingdom, the K. greatly relyes, which way he may promote the Faith without violence. Not long since ſome Catholick Peers did object to the K. that he made too much haſt to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Faith, to whom he anſwered, <hi>I growing old, muſt make great ſteps, otherwiſe, if I ſhould dye, I ſhall leave you worſe than I found you.</hi> Then they asking him why therefore was he not more ſolicitous for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of his Daughters Heirs of the Kingdom, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>God will take care for an Heir; leave my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for me to Convert; do you by your example reduce thoſe that are under you, and others to the Faith.</hi> In moſt Provinces he hath preferred Catholicks; and in a ſhort time we ſhall have the ſame Juſtices of the Peace (as they are called) in them all. At <hi>Oxford</hi> we hope Matters go very well: one of our Divines is always Reſident therein; a Publick Catholick Chappel of the Vice-Chancellor's, who hath drawn ſome Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents to the Faith. The Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi> ſeems very much to favour the Catholick Cauſe: he propoſed in Council, Whether it was not expedient, that at leaſt one Colledge in <hi>Oxford</hi> ſhould be allowed Catholicks, that they might not be forced to be at ſo much Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, by going beyond Seas to Study? what Anſwer was given, is not yet known. The ſame Biſhop invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting two of our Noblemen, with others of the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to a Banquet, drank the King's Health to an Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51366:2"/>Baron there, wiſhing a happy Succeſs to all His Affairs; and he added, That the Faith of Proteſtant in <hi>England,</hi> ſeemed to him to be little better than that of <hi>Buda</hi> was before it was taken; and that they were for the moſt part, mere Athieſts who defended it Many do embrace the Faith, and four of the chiefeſt Earls have lately profeſſed it publickly.</p>
               <p>The Reverend Father <hi>Alexander Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> Nephoy to our Provincial, to whom committed the Care of the Chappel, of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the Moſt Serene E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector Palatinate, is whole days buſied in reſolving, and ſhewing the Doubts or Queſtions of Hereticks, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Faith, of which number you may ſee two or three continually walking before the Dores of the Chappel, diſputing about Matters of Faith amongſt themſelves. Prince <hi>George,</hi> we can have nothing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain what Faith he intends to make Profeſſion of. We have a good while begun to get footing in <hi>England.</hi> We teach Humanity at <hi>Lincoln, Norwich,</hi> and <hi>York.</hi> At <hi>Warwick</hi> we have a Publick Chappel, ſecured from al Injuries by the King's Souldiers. We have alſo bought ſome Houſes of the City of <hi>Wiggorn,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Lancaſter.</hi> The Catholick Cauſe very much increaſeth. In ſome Catholick Churches, upon Holydays above 1500 are always numbred preſent at the Sermon. At <hi>London,</hi> likewiſe, things ſucceed no worſe. Every Holyday, at Preaching, People ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, that many of the Chappels cannot contain them. Two of ours, <hi>Darmes,</hi> and <hi>Berfall,</hi> do conſtantly ſay Maſs before the King and Queen Father <hi>Edmund New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>il</hi> before, the Queen Dowager, Father <hi>Alexander Regnes</hi> in the Chappel of the Ambaſſador aforeſaid, others in other places. Many Houſes are bought for the Colledge in the <hi>Savoy</hi> (as they call it) nigh <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet-houſe,</hi> London, the Palace of the Queen Dowa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, to the value of about eighteen thouſand <hi>Florins,</hi> in making of which after the Form of a Colledge, they labour very hard that the Schools may be opened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Eaſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhortly, there will be a Catholick Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, ſeeing no other can ſatisfie the King's Will to Eſtabliſh the Catholick Cauſe there, In the month of <hi>February,</hi> for certain, the King hath deſiged to call a Parliament at <hi>London:</hi> 1. That by a Univerſal Decree, the Catholick Peers may be admited into the Upper Houſe: 2. That the Oath or Teſt may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulled. 3. Which is the beſt or top of all, That all Penal Laws made againſt Catholicks, may be Abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; which that he may more ſurely obtain, he deſires every one to take notice, that he hath certainly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to, diſmiſs any from all profitable Imployments under him, who do not ſtrenuouſly, endeavour the obtaining thoſe things; alſo that he will Diſſolve the Parliament: with which Decree ſome Hereticks being affrighted, came to a certain Peer to conſult him what was Beſt to be done. to whom he ſaid, the Kings plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is ſufficiently made known to us; what he hath once ſaid, he will moſt certainly do: if you love your ſelves, you muſt ſubmit your ſelves to the Kings Will. There are great preparations for War at <hi>London,</hi> and a Squadron of many Ships of War are to be fitted out againſt a time appointed; what they are deſigned for is not certain. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> greatly fear they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, and the therefore begin to prepare themſelves, Time will diſcover more,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Liege,</hi> 
                     <date>2. <hi>Feb.</hi> 1688.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> A Letter from the Reverend Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Jeſuit, Almoner to the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> written to the Reverend Father <hi>la Chefe,</hi> Confeſſour to the <hi>Moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian King,</hi> touching the preſent Affairs of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">Tranſlated from the <hi>French.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Most Reverend Father,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF I have fail'd, for the laſt few days, to obſerve your Order, it was not from want of Affection, but Health, that occaſion'd the neglect; and for which I ſhall endeavour to make amends by the length of this.</p>
               <p>I ſhall begin where my former left off, and ſhall tell you, That ſince the appearing of a Letter in this Town, written by the Prince's Miniſter of <hi>Holland,</hi> which declares the Intentions of the Prince and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> relating to the Repealing of the <hi>Test,</hi> or to ſpeak more properly, their Averſion to it: This Letter has produc'd very ill effects among the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; whom, at the return of ſome of our Fathers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51366:2"/>from thoſe parts, we had perſwaded, that the Prince would comply with every thing relating to the <hi>Test,</hi> that the King ſhould propoſe to the next Parliament, in caſe he ſhould call one; to which I do not find his Majeſty much inclin'd. But the coming of this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (of which I have inclos'd a Copy) has ſerv'd for nothing but to incourage the Obſtinate in their averſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to that matter. The Queen, as well as myſelf, were of opinion, againſt the ſending of any ſuch Letter to the <hi>Hague,</hi> upon that ſubject, but rather that ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon able to diſcourſe and perſwade, ſhould have been ſent thither: for all ſuch Letters, when they are not grateful, produce bad effects. That which is ſpoken face to face, is not ſo eaſily divulg'd, nor any thing diſcover'd to the People, but what we have a mind the Vulgar ſhould know: And, I believe, your Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will concur with me in this opinion. This Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has extreamly provok'd the King, who is of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per not to bear a refuſal, and who has not been us'd to have his will contradicted: and, I verily believe, this very affront has haſtned his reſolution of re-calling the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Regiments in <hi>Holland.</hi> I ſhew'd his Majeſty that part of your Letter, that relates to the opinion of his <hi>Most Chriſtian Mejeſty,</hi> upon this ſubject, which his Majeſty well approves of. We are intereſted to know the ſucceſs of this affair, and what anſwer the States will give. The King changes as many Heretic Officers as he can, to put Catholics in their places; but the misfortune is, that here we want Catholic Officers to ſupply them: and therefore, if you know any ſuch of our Nation in <hi>France,</hi> you would do the King a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to perſwade them to come over, and they ſhall be certain of employments, either in the old Troops, or the new that are ſpeedily to be rais'd; for which, by this my Letter, I paſs my word.</p>
               <p>Our Fathers are continually employ'd to convert the Officers; but their obſtinacy is ſo great, that for one that turns, there are five that had rather quit their Commands. And there being ſo many Malecontents, whoſe party is already but too great, the King has need of all his prudence and temper, to manage this great affair, and bring it to that perfection we hope to ſee it in ere long. All that I can aſſure you is, That here ſhall be no neglect in the Queen, who labours night and day, with unexpreſſible diligence, for the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Faith, and with the zeal of a holy Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs The Queen Dowager is not ſo earneſt; and fear makes her reſolve to retire into <hi>Portugal,</hi> to paſs the remainder of her days in Devotion: ſhe has already ask'd the King leave, who has not only granted it, but alſo promiſed, that ſhe ſhall have her Penſion punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally paid; and that during her life, her Servants that ſhe leaves behind her, ſhall have the ſame Wages, as if they were in waiting. She ſtays but for a proper ſeaſon to imbark for <hi>Lisbon,</hi> and to live there free from all ſtories.</p>
               <p>As to the Queen's being with Child, that great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern gaes as well as we could wiſh, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the ſatyrical Diſcourſes of the Heretics, who content themſelves to vent their poyſon in Libels, which by night they diſperſe in the Street, or fix upon the Walls. There was one lately found upon a Pillar of a Church, that imported, That ſuch a day, Thanks ſhould be given to GOD, for the Queen's being great with a Cuſhion. If one of theſe Paſquil-makers could be diſcover'd, he would but have in Ill time on't, and ſhould be made to take his laſt farewel at <hi>Tyburn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You will agree with me (moſt Reverend Father) that we have done a great thing, by introducing <hi>Mrs. Celier</hi> to the Queen: this woman is totally devoted to our Society, and zealous for the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Religion. I will ſend you an account of the progreſs of this Affair, and will uſe the Cypher you ſent me, which I think admirable. I can ſend you nothing certain of the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Denmark;</hi> he is a Prince with whom I cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about Religion; <hi>Luther</hi> was never more earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, than this Prince. It is for this reaſon that the King (who does not love to be denied) never yet preſs'd him in that matter, his Majeſty thinking it neceſſary that the Fathers ſhold firſt prepare things, before he undertake to ſpeak to him. But this Prince, as all of his Nation, has naturally an averſion to our Society; and this antipathy does much obſtruct the progreſs of our Affairs; and it would be unreaſonable to complain hereof to the King, at preſent to trouble him, though he has an intire confidence in us, and looks upon our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as the Apoſtles of this Land. As for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> that Country is already all Catholic; yea, all the Militia are ſo. The Vice-Roy merits great praiſe; we may give him this honour, That he is a Son worthy our Society; and I hope will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of the Merits of it. He informs me, he has juſt writ to your Reverence of thoſe matters, how things go there. Some Catholic Regiments from thoſe parts will ſpeedily be ſent for over, for the King's Guards; his Majeſtly being reſolv'd to truſt them, rather than others; and may do it better, in caſe of any popular Commotion, againſt which we ought to ſecure ourſelves the beſt we can. His Majeſtly does us the honour to viſit our Colledge often, and is moſt pleas'd when we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him ſome new Convert-ſcholars; whom he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages with his gracious promiſes. I have not expreſſion ſufficient to let you know, with what Devotion his Majeſty communicated the laſt Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days; and a Heretic cannot better make his court to him, than by turning to the Catholic Faith. He deſires that all the Religions, of what Order ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they be, make open profeſſion, as he does, not only of the Catholic Religion, but alſo of their Order; not at all approving that Prieſts, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51366:3"/>ſhould conceal themſelves, out of fear; and he has told them, That he would have them wear the Habit of a Religious; and that he will take care to defend them from affronts. And the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are already accuſtomed to it; and we begin to celebrate Funerals with the ſame Ceremony as in <hi>France;</hi> but it is almoſt a Miracle to ſee that no body ſpeaks one, word againſt it, no not ſo much as the Miniſters in their Pulpits; in ſo good order has the King managed theſe matters. Many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Heretics reſort often to our Sermons; and I have often recommended to our Fathers, to preach, now in the beginning, as little as they can of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, becauſe that provokes; but to repreſent to them the Beauty and Antiquity of the Catholic Religion, that they may be convinc'd that all that has been ſaid and preach'd to them, and their own Reflections concerning it, have been all ſcandal: For I find (as the Apoſtle ſays) they muſt be nouriſh'd with Milk, not being able to bear ſtrong Meat. Many have deſir'd me to give them ſome of our Prayers, and even the holy Maſs, in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh:</hi> which I mean to do, to ſatisfie the meaneſt ſort, of which the greateſt part do not underſtand <hi>Latine,</hi> but not to take away from the new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts their Teſtaments, which is a matter of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and, that we may not diſguſt them at the beginning, we muſt permit them to have them for a time, till they part with them of themſelves. I have need of <hi>C. H.</hi>'s counſel upon this point, and not in this only, but alſo in a great many other matters that daily preſs me: for you may eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that I have often more buſineſs than I can well diſpatch; and we muſt work with ſo much circumſpection and precaution, that I have often need of your Paternity's wiſe counſel. But the Lord, and the good Virgin do ſtrengthen me as there is occaſion.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Oxon</hi> has not yet declar'd himſelf openly; the great obſtacle is his Wife, whom he cannot rid himſelf of: His deſign being to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue Biſhop, and only change Communion; as it not doubted but the King will permit, and our holy Father confirm: though I do not ſee how he can be farther uſeful to us, in the Religion in which he is, becauſe he is ſuſpected, and of no eſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Heretics of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church: nor do I ſee that the example of his Converſion is like to draw many others after him, becauſe he declar'd himſelf ſo ſuddenly. If he had believ'd my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, which was to temporize for ſome longer time, he would have done better; but it is his temper, or rather zeal that hurried him on. There are two other Prelates that will do no leſs than he; but they hold off alike, to ſee how they may be ſerviceable to the propagation, and produce more fruits, while they continue undiſcover'd.</p>
               <p>That which does us moſt harm with the Lords and great men, is the apprehenſion of a Heretic Succeſſour: <hi>For,</hi> (as a Lord told me lately) <hi>aſſure me of a Catholic Succeſſour, and I will aſſure you, I and my Family will be ſo too.</hi> To this happy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, the Queen's happy delivery will be of very great moment. Our zealous Catholics do already lay two to one, that it will be a Prince: GOD does nothing by halves; and every day Maſſes are ſaid upon this very occaſion.</p>
               <p>I have gain'd a very great point, in perſwading the King to place our Fathers in <hi>Magdalen-Celledge</hi> in <hi>Oxon;</hi> who will be able to tutor the young Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in the Roman Catholic Religion. I rely much on Father <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> to whom I have given neceſſary Inſtructions how to govern himſelf with the Heretic People; and to take care, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, that he ſpeak not to them any thing that may terrifie. And, as I tell you , a Religious has need here of great prudence, at this time, that the King may hear of no Complaints that may diſpleaſe him; and therefore we dare not at preſent, do all we ſhall be able, and bound to do hereafter, for fear of too much haring the Mobile.</p>
               <p>I like well that Father <hi>Hales</hi> goes to ſtay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time at the <hi>Hague Incognito,</hi> on pretence of ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for a Place, which is not ſoon to be got there; and I have given him a Letter to ſome of that Court: Father <hi>Smith</hi> that is there now, by reaſon of his great Age, nor being able to do all he ought and wiſhes to do, and is alſo too well known there. And I ſhall often impart to you what I ſhall learn from thoſe Quarters: from whence I ſhall weekly receive ſomething of moment, ſo long as the two Courts are in ſo bad Intelligence together, as at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent they are. For my part, to ſpeak freely on this Topick to your Reverend Fatherhood, I am of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, we ſhould rather endeavour to Moderate, than Aggravate the Difference between them; tho' I know I do not, in this matter, altogether concur with the Sence of the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſadour, who conſiders only his Maſter's Intereſt: But we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated to take other Meaſures, and ſuch as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may not always agree with the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> in this matter.</p>
               <p>And I think aggravating of this Breach at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, to be alſo prejudicial to the Catholick Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on itſelf. The great deſign we have ſo long aimed at, is applying to the King of <hi>France</hi> to take from the Hereticks all hopes of a Head, or any other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, than what they muſt expect from their own King; whereby they, finding themſelves expes'd to his Pleaſure, will the more readily ſubſcribe to his Will. But this miſunderſtanding between us, will occaſion an opportunity to the Heretics to ſet up the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> for their Chief. And let me aſſure you, not to deceive yourſelves, The Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51366:3"/>of <hi>England,</hi> as well as the Presbyterians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, regard the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> as their <hi>Moſes;</hi> and his Party is already ſo powerful in both theſe Kingdoms, that it will appear terrible to any think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon, ſhould things come to extremity; as may never happen, if matters are not puſh'd on too far, but managed with Moderation. And I deſire therefore, with great deference to your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgment, that this matter might be hinted to his <hi>Most Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> as opportunity ſhall ſerve, and am ſenſible it muſt be done with very great caution.</p>
               <p>I can tell you nothing at preſent concerning the certainty of calling a Parliament; it requires ſo many things to be conſider'd of, and meaſures to be taken, that his Majeſty ought to be well aſſur'd of the ſucceſs, before he Convenes them together. I am not of opinion with many other Catholics, who ſay, That by calling them, the King hazards nothing; for, if they will not anſwer his ends, he need only Prorogue them, as is uſually done: But it is my opinion, and the ſence of many others, That his Majeſty hazards- much; for if it ſhould unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately happen, that they ſhould, in their Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, refuſe to comply with his Majeſty's deſires, it may be long enough ere he compaſs his ends by way of a Parliament, and perhaps never: and then there reſts no expedient, or other means, but by Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to execute the Orders of his ſecret Council, which muſt be ſuppos'd by his Army; who, upon a pretence of Incamping, may be called together with the leſs jealouſie or ſuſpicion. So, you may ſee (moſt Reverend Father) that we do not want work in theſe Quarters; and I muſt be ſupported by your Prayers, which I beg of you, and from all thoſe of our Society.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty is ſo deſirous that things may be done in order, and upon a ſure fund, ſo as to be the more laſting, that he makes great application to the Shires and Corporations, to get ſuch perſons choſen for the Parliament, as may be favourable to his ends, of which he may be ſure, before they come to debate: And the King will make them promiſe ſo firmly, and exact ſuch Inſtruments from them in writing, that they ſhall not be able to go back, unleſs they will thereby draw upon themſelves his Majeſty's utmoſt diſpleaſure, and make them feel the weight of his reſentment. And I have here inclos'd ſome effects of his Majeſty's endeavours in this matter, which is an Addreſs which the Mayor, Sheriffs and Burgeſſes of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> in the County of <hi>Stafford,</hi> have preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the King, [ſee the <hi>Gazette,</hi> where this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, as well as <hi>Glocaſter</hi> and <hi>Teuxbury,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, in their Addreſſes, promiſe to chooſe ſuch Members as ſhall comply with his Majeſty's deſires] If all Towns were in as perfect Obedience as theſe, we ſhould certainly have a Parliament call'd, which the Catholics and Non-conformiſts expect with great impatience. But, ſince this cannot be ſaid of many of them, the King's Secret Council think good to wait for the Queen's delivery, that they may ſee a Succeſſour, who may have need of the whole Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Most Chriſtian King</hi> to ſupport him, and maintain his Rights. And, by the Grace of GOD, we hope, that that Prince, treading in his Father's ſteps, may prove a worthy Son of our Society, like his Father, who thinks it no diſhonour to be ſo call'd.</p>
               <p>As to other things, (moſt Reverend Father) our Fathers, with me, as well as generally all the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lics, with what grief do we hear of the Diſ-union that ariſes between his Holineſs and the <hi>Most Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King!</hi> How does my head, in imitation of the Prophet's, become a Spring of Tears to lament night and day the Schiſm that I foreſee coming into the Church! Is it poſſible that our holy Society ſhould not ſtand in the Breach, and prevent the miſchiefs that this Difference may occaſion in the Church? And that no body can reconcile <hi>Levi</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> the Prieſthood and the Scepter, the Father and the Son, the eldeſt Son of the Church with the Vicar of Chriſt upon Earth? And what a Deſolation, and what Advantage to the Hereties, muſt this occaſion? They begin already to bid us Convert the Children of the Family, before we begin to Convert Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. And I muſt with grief confeſs, they have but too much reaſon for what they ſay; and if there does not come ſome preſent aſſiſtance from Above, I foreſee this Affair will occaſion great prejudices in the <hi>North:</hi> Nor have we any hope, that his <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Majeſty will interpoſe herein openly, he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo little ſatisfaction from his Holineſs, in ſome demands made by his Ambaſſadour at <hi>Rome,</hi> which (morally ſpeaking) ought not to have been denied ſo great a King, who firſt made this ſtep, (which his Predeceſſours for a long time were not willing to undertake) in ſending his Ambaſſadour of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to <hi>Rome:</hi> And yet, for all this, our holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had nor any particular conſideration of this Submiſſion and Filial Obedience: ſo that I dare not mention this matter, but by way of diſcourſe, daily expecting that of himſelf he will be pleas'd to make ſome Propoſal therein. I doubt not (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father) of your conſtant endeavour to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate this matter, thereby to take away from the Heretics, eſpecially the <hi>Hugonots of France,</hi> this occaſion to laugh and deride us: and we ſhould think the change much for the worſe, if, inſtead of the <hi>French</hi> King's going to <hi>Geneva,</hi> he ſhould march to <hi>Rome:</hi> What may not all this come to? eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince the Marqueſs <hi>de Lavardin</hi> has been ſo paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate in his diſcourſe to the Cardinal Chancellour, as to call him Impertinent; and ſo far to forget his Duty and Reverence toward our holy Father, the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51366:4"/>Pope himſelf, as to ſay he Doted: as the Heretics do confidently diſcourſe in theſe parts. I have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſome Maſſes of Holy Ghoſt to be ſaid, That GOD would pleaſe to Inſpire the diſcontented Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with a Spirit of Peace and Concord. You did acquaint me, ſome time ſince, That Madam <hi>Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> did take upon her the Title of <hi>Daughter of the Society;</hi> by vertue whereof, you may command her, by vertue of Obedience, to uſe her Credit and Eloquence with the King, to incline him to an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation in this matter. In the mean time, I hear that at <hi>Rome,</hi> many eminent perſons endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the ſame with his Holineſs, who ſays, He can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor ought not to recede from what he has done; otherwiſe, it were in effect to ſubmit to the Articles made in <hi>France</hi> by the Clergy in 1682, and conſequently of too great moment to recant: and therefore, Submiſſion ought to come from the Son, and not from the Father. I recommend myſelf (Reverend Father) to your Prayers and Bleſſing, deſiring you would continue to aſſiſt me with your Salutal Counſels, and reſt for ever</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>St. <hi>James</hi>'s, <date>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 9th.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> The Anſwer of the Reverend Father <hi>la Cheſe,</hi> Confeſſour to the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King,</hi> to a Letter of the Reverend Father <hi>Petre,</hi> Jeſuit, and Great Almoner to the King of <hi>England,</hi> upon the Method or Rule he must obſerve with His Majeſty, for the Converſion of His Proteſtant Subjects.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Most Reverend Father,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WHen I compare the Method of the <hi>French</hi> Court (which declares againſt all Hereſies) with the Policy of other Princes, who had the ſame Deſign in former Ages; I find ſo great a difference that all that paſſes now a days in the King's Council is an impenetrable Miſtery: and the eyes of all <hi>Europe</hi> are opened, to ſee what happens; but cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, and <hi>Henry</hi> the Second his Son; undertook to Ruine the Reformation, they had to ſtruggle with a Party which was but begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and weak, and deſtitute of Help; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently eaſier to be overcome.</p>
               <p>In the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the Second, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth, a Family was ſeen advanc'd to the Throne by the Ruine of the Proteſtants, who were for the Houſe of <hi>Bourbon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this laſt Reign many Maſſacres hapned, and ſeveral Millions of Hereticks have been Sacrificed, but it anſwer'd otherways: and his Majeſty has ſhow'd (by the peace and mild ways he uſes) that he abhors ſhedding of Blood; from which you muſt perſwade his <hi>Britannic</hi> Majeſty, who naturally is inclined to Roughneſs, and a kind of Boldneſs, which will make him hazard all, if he does not Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litickly manage it; as I hinted in my laſt, when I mentioned my Lord Chancellor.</p>
               <p>Moſt Reverend Father, to ſatisfie the deſire I have to ſhew you by my Letters the Choice you ought to make of ſuch Perſons fit to ſtir up, I will in few words (ſince you deſire it) inform you of the Genius of the People of our Court, of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and which of them we make uſe of; that by a Parallel which you will make, between them and your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Lords, you may learn to know them.</p>
               <p>Therefore I ſhall begin with the Chief: I mean, our Great Monarch. It is certain that he is natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally good, and loves not to do Evil, unleſs deſir'd to do it. This being ſo, I may ſay, he never would have undertaken the Converſion of his Subjects, without the Clergy of <hi>France,</hi> and without our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties Correſpondence abroad. He is a Prince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned; who very well obſerves, that what we put him upon, is contrary to his Intereſt, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more oppoſite to his Great Deſigns, and his Glory; he aiming to be the Terror of all <hi>Europe.</hi> The vaſt number of Malecontents he has cauſed in his Kingdom, forces him in time of Peace to keep three times more Forces, than his Anceſtors did in the greateſt Domeſtick and Foreign Wars: which cannot be done, without a prodigious Expence.</p>
               <p>The Peoples Feats alſo begin to leſſen, as to his Aſpiring to an Univerſal Monarchy: and they may aſſure themſelves he has left thoſe thoughts; nothing being more oppoſite to his Deſigns, than the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod we enjoyn him. His Candor, Bounty, and To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, to the Hereticks, would undoubtedly have open'd the doors of the Low Countries, <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and all other States on the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and even of <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland:</hi> whereas things are at preſent ſo alter'd, that we ſee the <hi>Hollanders</hi> free from any fear of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51366:4"/>danger; the <hi>Switzers</hi> and City of <hi>Geneva,</hi> reſolv'd to loſe the laſt drop of their Blood in their defence; beſides ſome diverſion we may expect from the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, in caſe we cannot hinder a Peace with the <hi>Turks;</hi> which ought to haſten his <hi>Britannick</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, while he can be aſſured of Succors from the moſt Chriſtian King.</p>
               <p>Sir, his Majeſties Brother is always the ſame, I mean, takes no notice of what paſſes at Court. It has ſometimes happen'd, that Kings Brothers have act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo, as to be noted in the State; but this we may be aſſur'd will never do any thing to ſtain the glory of his Submiſſion and Obedience: and is willing to lend a helping hand for the Deſtruction of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks; which appears by the inſtances he makes to his Majeſty, who now has promiſed him to cauſe his Troops to enter into the <hi>Palatinate</hi> the next Month.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dauphin</hi> is paſſionately given up to Hunting, and little regards the Converſion of Souls; and it does not ſeem eaſie to make him penetrate into bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of Moment; and therefore we do not care to conſult him which way, and how, the Hereticks ought to be Treated. He openly laughs at us, and ſights all the Deſigns, of which the King his Father makes great account. The Dauphineſs is extreamly witty; and is without doubt uneaſie to ſhew it in other matters beſides Complements of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. She has given me a Letter for the Queen of <hi>England;</hi> wherein after her expreſſion of the part ſhe bears on the news of her Majeſties being with Child, ſhe gives her ſeveral advices about the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of her Subjects.</p>
               <p>Moſt Reverend Father, She is undoubtedly born a great enemy to the Proteſtants; and has promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all ſhe could with his Majeſty, in all that has been done, to haſten their Ruine; eſpecially having been bred in a Court of our Society, and of a Houſe whoſe hatred againſt the Proteſtant Religion is Hereditary; becauſe ſhe has been raiſed up by the Ruine of the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtant Princes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that of the <hi>Palatinate.</hi> But the King having cauſed her to come to make Heirs to the Crown, ſhe anſwers expectation to the utmoſt.</p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>Louvois</hi> is a man who very much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his duty, which he performs to admiration; and to whom we muſt acknowledge <hi>France</hi> owes part of the glory it has hitherto gained, both in regard of its Conqueſts, as alſo the Converſion of Hereticks; to which latter I may ſay, he has con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed as much as the King: he has already ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf Fierce, Wrathful, and Hardhearted, in his Actions towards them; though he is not natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally inclin'd to Cruelty, nor to harraſs the people. His Brother the Archbiſhop of <hi>Rheims,</hi> has ways which do not much differ from thoſe of his Soul; and all the difference I find between them is, That the Archbiſhop loves his own glory, as much as Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Louvois</hi> loves that of his Majeſty. He is his own Idol; and give him but Incenſe, and you may obtain any thing. Honour is welcome to him, let it come which way it will. The leaſt thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes this Prelate; and he will not yield any thing deregotary to his Paternity. He will ſeem Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; he will ſeem a great <hi>Theologian,</hi> and will ſeem to be a good Biſhop, and to have a great care of his Dioceſs; and would heretofore ſeem a great Preacher. I have hinted in my laſt, the Reaſons why I cannot altogether like him; which are need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to repeat.</p>
               <p>The Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> is always the ſame; I mean, a gallant man; whoſe preſent Converſation is charming, and loves his pleaſures; but cannot bear any thing that grieves or gives trouble; though he is always a great enemy of the <hi>Janſeniſts,</hi> which he lately intimated to Cardinal <hi>Camus.</hi> He is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with me in the Council of Conſcience, and agrees very well with our Society; laying moſtly to heart the Converſion of the Proteſtants of the three Kingdoms. He alſo makes very good Obſervations, and deſigns to give ſome Advice to your Reverence, which I ſhall convey to you. I do ſometimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to him, what you write to me.</p>
               <p>My Lord <hi>Kingſton</hi> has embrac'd our good Party: I was preſent when he Abjur'd in the Church of St. <hi>Denys;</hi> I will give you the Circumſtances ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
               <p>You promiſed to ſend me the Names of all He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick Officers who are in his Majeſties Troops; that much imports me; and you ſhall not want good Catholick Officers to fill up their Places I have drawn a Liſt of them who are to paſs into <hi>England;</hi> and his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty approves, thereof: Pray obſerve what I hinted to you in my laſt, on the Subject of the Viſits, which our Fathers muſt give to the Chief Lords, Members of the next Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; thoſe Reverend Fathers, who are to perform that duty, muſt be middle aged, with a lively Countenance, and fit to perſwade. I alſo adviſed you in ſome of my other Letters how the Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi> ought to behave himſelf, by Writing inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly, and to inſinuate into the people the putting down the Teſt; and at the ſame time calm the ſtorm, which the Letter of Penſionary <hi>Fag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> has raiſed. And his Majeſty muſt continue to make vigorous Prohibitions to all Bookſellers in <hi>London,</hi> not to print any Anſwers: as well to put a ſtop to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency of Heretick Authors; as alſo to hinder the people from Reading them.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, you intimate to me, That his Majeſty will-follow our Advice: It's the quickeſt way, and I cannot find a better, or fitter, to diſpoſſeſs his Subjects from ſuch Impreſſions as they have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. His Majeſty muſt alſo, by the ſame Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51366:5"/>profeſs in Conſcience, that (if complyed with) he will not only keep his Word, to maintain and protect the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but will alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his Promiſes by ſuch Laws, as the Proteſtants ſhall be contented with. This is the true Politick way; for by his granting all, they cannot but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſomething.</p>
               <p>His moſt Chriſtian Majeſty has with great ſucceſs experienced this Maxim: and though he had not to ſtruggle with Penal Laws and Teſts, yet he found it convenient to make large Promiſes, by many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations; for, ſince we muſt diſſemble, you muſt endeavour all you can to perſwade the King, it is the only method to effect his Deſigns.</p>
               <p>I did alſo in my laſt, give you a hint of its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, as well as the ways you muſt take to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate your ſelves dextrouſly with the King, to gain his good will I know not whether you have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what paſſed in <hi>England</hi> ſome years ſince, I will recite it, becauſe Examples inſtruct much.</p>
               <p>One of our Aſſiſting Fathers of that Kingdom, (which was Father <hi>Parſons</hi>) having written a Book againſt the Succeſſion of the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> to the Realm of <hi>England:</hi> Father <hi>Creighton,</hi> who was alſo of our Society, and upheld by many of our Party, defended the Cauſe of that King, in a Book Intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Reaſons of the King of Scots, againſt the Book of Father Parſons:</hi> and though they ſeem'd divided, yet they underſtood one another very well; this being practiced by order of our General, to the end, that if the Houſe of <hi>Scotland</hi> were Exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they might ſhew him who had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Book of Father <hi>Parſons;</hi> and on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, if the King hapned to be reſtored to the Throne, they might obtain his good will, by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him the Works of Father <hi>Creighton:</hi> So that which way ſoever the Medal turn'd, it ſtill prov'd to the advantage of our Society. Not to digreſs from our ſubject, I muſt deſire you to read the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Book of Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> Intituled, <hi>The Reform of England;</hi> where, after his blaming of Cardinal <hi>Pole,</hi> and made ſome obſervations of Faults in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> he finally concludes, That ſuppoſe <hi>England</hi> ſhould return (as we hope) to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith in this Reign, he would reduce it to the State of the Primitive Church: and to that end all the Eccleſiaſtical Revenue ought to be uſed in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and the Management thereof committed to the care of Seven Wiſe Men, drawn out of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, to be diſpoſed of by them as they ſhould think fit. Moreover, he would have all the Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders forbidden on Religious Penalties, not to return into the Three Kingdoms, without leave of thoſe Seaven Wiſe Men: to the end, it might be granted only to ſuch as live on Alms. Theſe Reflections ſeem to me very Judicious, and very ſuitable to the preſent State of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Father <hi>Parſons</hi> adds, That when <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> is reduced to the True Faith, the Pope muſt not expect, at leaſt for Five years, to reap any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the Eccleſiaſtical Revenue; but muſt leave the whole in the hands of thoſe Seven Wiſe Men; who will manage the ſame to the Benefit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Church.</p>
               <p>The Court goes this day for <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li,</hi> to take the Divertiſements which are there prepared: I hope to accompany the King, and will entertain him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout all buſineſs; and accordingly as he likes what you hint to me in your Letter, I ſhall give you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. I have acquainted him with his <hi>Britannic</hi> Majeſties Deſign, of Building a Citadel near <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall;</hi> Monſieur <hi>Vauban,</hi> our Engineer was preſent: after ſome Diſcourſe on the Importance of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, his Majeſty told Monſieur <hi>Vauban,</hi> that he thought it convenient he ſhould make a Model of the Deſign, and that he ſhould on purpoſe go over into <hi>England,</hi> to ſee the Ground. I have done all I could to ſuſpend the Deſigns of our Great Monarch, who is always angry againſt the Holy Father: both Parties are ſtubborn: the Kings natural Inclination is, to have all yield to him; and the Popes Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is unalterable.</p>
               <p>All our Fathers moſt humbly ſalute your Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Father <hi>Roine Ville</hi> acts wonderfully about <hi>Niſmes</hi> amongſt the New Converts; who ſtill meet, notwithſtanding the Danger they expoſe themſelves to. I daily expect News from the Frontiers of the Empire, which I ſhall impart to your Reverence, and am with the greateſt Reſpect,</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Paris</hi> 
                     <date>
                        <hi>March</hi> 7. 1688.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
